<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Ashwini's blog - Business &amp; Leadership</title><link href="https://ashwch.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://ashwch.com/feeds/business-leadership.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://ashwch.com/</id><updated>2025-03-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Actionable Insights from Jeff Bezos' Interview at the DealBook Summit</title><link href="https://ashwch.com/actionable-insights-jeff-bezos-dealbook-summit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-03-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-03-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Ashwini Chaudhary</name></author><id>tag:ashwch.com,2025-03-10:/actionable-insights-jeff-bezos-dealbook-summit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Actionable Insights from Jeff Bezos' Interview at the DealBook Summit.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Risk is often overestimated; opportunity is often underestimated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Podcast: &lt;a href="https://www.founderspodcast.com/episodes/374-rare-jeff-bezos-interview"&gt;https://www.founderspodcast.com/episodes/374-rare-jeff-bezos-interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;YouTube: &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/s71nJQqzYRQ"&gt;https://youtu.be/s71nJQqzYRQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Build something that outlasts you&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since early days of Amazon Bezos was thinking long-term and was quite clear that he wanted to build a company that would outlast him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spotify's Daniel Ek shares a similar sentiment: Companies grow like children — initially they are a reflection of their creator, but over time they develops its own traits and characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Jobs said something similar: You build a company that will stand for something a generation or two from now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Follow your curiosity&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of his driving principles is "I wake up and follow my curiosity".  Paul Graham calls curiosity the best guide for doing &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of over-analyzing your next move, follow your curiosity and let that be your compass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;AI is the new electricity&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He describes AI as just an horizontal enabling layer, just like electricity. When electricity came out, people only wanted light bulbs; everything else came after. People weren't putting electricity in their homes; they were putting light bulbs in their homes. At that point they weren't even thinking of appliances, switchboard or anything, and there wasn't even a concept of off switch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, AI, like electricity before, will be embedded into everything, transforming industries in unpredictable ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If AI is an enabling layer, ask: How can AI supercharge my business, my workflows, my products?_ The most valuable companies of the next decade will answer this question well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link to his 2003 TED talk: &lt;a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/jeff_bezos_the_electricity_metaphor_for_the_web_s_future"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The AWS Insight: Computing as a Utility&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His inspiration for AWS came from a 300 year old Luxembourg brewery that had its own power generator -- because at that time, there were no power grids. Similarly, before AWS companies had their own data center and he realized that it's not going to last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That meant companies had to focus on something that wasn't their core business, true for anything in the past that had to worry about generating their own electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Power of Being Misunderstood&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has long accepted that he will be misunderstood. He prioritizes doing what he believes is right over chasing a good PR. He said, if even your closest loved ones do not fully know you, how can you expect others to understand you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warren Buffett and Charlie Munger have similar philosophy. They keep an inner scorecard -- measuring success by their own principles, not external validation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If no one skeptical about what you're doing, you're probably not pushing hard enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Meetings Should Be Messy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He insists that meetings should wander, and people should not come into meetings with rehearsed responses. He also always speaks last and is always asking if anyone has any dissenting opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meetings should be raw, unfiltered and people should feel comfortable challenging ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Optimism is a Moral Duty&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edwin Land, Steve Jobs' hero, believed that "optimism is a moral duty". Bezos embodies this mindset, he truly believes there has never been a better time to be alive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As a leader, you need to exude optimism. Ambitious projects require an unshakeable belief in a better future.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Every Decision is an Opportunity Cost&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He explains why he does so few interview. &lt;em&gt;"Every minute I'm doing this, I'm not spending that time doing something else"&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time is your most valuable resource — guard it fiercely. Choose only what moves the needle for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Ferocious Intelligence&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charlie Munger once said,  &lt;em&gt;"He is ferociously intelligent&lt;/em&gt;."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relentless curiosity, optimism, and long-term thinking are what makes Bezos worth studying. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Business &amp; Leadership"></category><category term="jeff-bezos"></category><category term="entrepreneurship"></category><category term="long-term-thinking"></category><category term="company-building"></category><category term="ai-revolution"></category><category term="innovation"></category><category term="curiosity"></category><category term="optimism"></category><category term="opportunity-cost"></category><category term="blue-origin"></category><category term="amazon"></category><category term="leadership"></category><category term="decision-making"></category><category term="business-strategy"></category><category term="meetings"></category><category term="bezos-quotes"></category><category term="charlie-munger"></category><category term="warren-buffett"></category><category term="technology"></category><category term="invention"></category><category term="future-thinking"></category><category term="risk-taking"></category><category term="wealth-creation"></category><category term="podcast"></category><category term="founders-podcast"></category></entry></feed>