<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Ashwini's blog - Productivity, Self-Improvement, Life Lessons</title><link href="https://ashwch.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://ashwch.com/feeds/productivity-self-improvement-life-lessons.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://ashwch.com/</id><updated>2025-03-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Designing a Life: Lessons from Benjamin Franklin</title><link href="https://ashwch.com/life-lessons-benjamin-franklin.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-03-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-03-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Ashwini Chaudhary</name></author><id>tag:ashwch.com,2025-03-26:/life-lessons-benjamin-franklin.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;How Benjamin Franklin designed his life, built habits, and used humor, curiosity, and community to continuously reinvent himself.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Before listening to &lt;a href="https://www.takeoverpod.com/episodes/benjamin-franklin"&gt;&lt;em&gt;How to Take Over the World&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;'s episode on Benjamin Franklin, my impression of him was limited to “kite, key, electricity.” Afterward, I realized he didn't just discover electricity -- he basically invented the blueprint for self-improvement, then actually lived it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He wasn't just an inventor; he created institutions and actively built himself. And he did it in a way that it feels surprisingly relevant today, without losing his sense of humour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some things that stuck with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Benjamin Franklin: The Original Self-Made Person&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He's the most literal example of self-made people. He didn't just bootstrap a career, he designed who he wanted to be and iterated toward it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one point in his life, he wrote out a list of 13 virtues. Things like temperance, resolution, industry, humility. And then created a tracking system to improve one per week. Like a habit tracker, but from the 1700s. He had a grid and he reviewed it nightly. He built an internal feedback loop before we had that language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did it make him perfect? Not even close. But &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/426224-but-on-the-whole-though-i-never-arrived-at-the"&gt;he said something&lt;/a&gt; that stuck with me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But on the whole, though I never arrived at the perfection I had been so ambitious of obtaining, but fell far short of it, yet I was, by the endeavour, a better and happier man than I otherwise should have been had I not attempted it; as those who aim at perfect writing by imitating the engraved copies, their hand is mended by the endeavour, and is tolerable while it continues fair and legible”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Learning by reverse-engineering&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Franklin taught himself how to write by reading essays in &lt;em&gt;The Spectator&lt;/em&gt;. He used to summarize the key arguments, and then he would try to rewrite the entire piece from scratch a few days later. Then he'd compare his version with the original and note where he went wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a simple yet brilliant way to learn. He built muscle memory towards it with this approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Curious, Playful, and Unafraid to Experiment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my favorite part from the episode. Franklin did what interested him, even if it didn't have any obvious ROI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone once asked him why he was experimenting with hot air balloons, and he responded:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What is the use of a newborn baby?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He just liked it and trusted that something good would come out of following that instinct. Which is actually how most breakthroughs happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most productive people aren't just focussed on productivity, they are the ones who still let them chase just because it's fun or weird or fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Peer-driven growth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Franklin started something called the Junto. It was a group of ambitious, curious people who met weekly to debate ideas, share essays, and challenge each other to improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This wasn't about ego or point-scoring. The rule was: no arguing, no personal attacks, no pretending you're the smartest person in the room. Just honest enquiry and curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Junto lasted for 40 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it wasn’t just talk -- real things came out of it. The idea for America’s first subscription library was born in the Junto and became the Library Company of Philadelphia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Serious About Humour&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Franklin was funny, like actually funny. But he didn't use it just to entertain -- it was how he disarmed people, made ideas stick, and built a public persona people trusted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he was 15, he wrote letters under the name &lt;em&gt;Silence Dogood&lt;/em&gt; and dropped them anonymously on the doorstep of his brother’s print shop. They were supposedly written by a widowed woman who was “handsome and sometimes witty.” That “sometimes” kills me. It’s the perfect character detail, funny, self-aware, instantly charming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later, as the fake author of &lt;em&gt;Poor Richard’s Almanack&lt;/em&gt;, he’d write snarky fake feuds with imaginary critics. One of my favorites: he predicted another writer’s death, then when the guy wrote in angry that he was very much alive, Franklin insisted the letter must be a forgery -- because the real man would never write so poorly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Franklin didn’t take himself too seriously.  And that &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; part of his power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His charm made people want to read him. It made political enemies underestimate him. And it made allies feel like they were in on the joke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a world full of Very Serious Men trying to win arguments, Franklin laughed -- and then won anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lessons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Franklin wasn’t just a scientist, or a writer, or a politician, or a businessman. He was all of those things. But more than anything, he was a systems thinker for human life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He designed how he lived.&lt;br&gt;
He chased what made him curious.&lt;br&gt;
He got better in public.&lt;br&gt;
He didn't pretend to be perfect.&lt;br&gt;
And he never let ambition overshadow joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a good model:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create structures that support your growth.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    Build your own systems—track habits, design feedback loops, give your goals shape.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Form communities that push you forward.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    Don’t just network. Find people who challenge, teach, and grow with you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chase ideas without obsessing over immediate ROI.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    Some of the most useful things start as playful experiments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep improving, even if you’ll never be perfect.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    Progress matters more than perfection. The act of trying changes you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t wait for permission to reinvent yourself.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    Franklin didn’t. You don’t need anyone’s blessing to evolve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use humor as a strategic advantage.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
    Be sharp, but approachable. Laugh. It makes people listen -- and keeps you human.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benjamin Franklin didn't just build a remarkable life -- he left behind a blueprint we can all still follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The 13 virtues&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Temperance&lt;/strong&gt; – Eat not to dullness; drink not to elevation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Silence&lt;/strong&gt; – Speak not but what may benefit others or yourself; avoid trifling conversation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Order&lt;/strong&gt; – Let all your things have their places; let each part of your business have its time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resolution&lt;/strong&gt; – Resolve to perform what you ought; perform without fail what you resolve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frugality&lt;/strong&gt; – Make no expense but to do good to others or yourself; waste nothing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industry&lt;/strong&gt; – Lose no time; be always employed in something useful; cut off all unnecessary actions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sincerity&lt;/strong&gt; – Use no hurtful deceit; think innocently and justly, and, if you speak, speak accordingly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Justice&lt;/strong&gt; – Wrong none by doing injuries or omitting the benefits that are your duty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moderation&lt;/strong&gt; – Avoid extremes; forbear resenting injuries so much as you think they deserve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cleanliness&lt;/strong&gt; – Tolerate no uncleanliness in body, clothes, or habitation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tranquillity&lt;/strong&gt; – Be not disturbed at trifles or at accidents common or unavoidable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chastity&lt;/strong&gt; – Rarely use venery (sexual indulgence) but for health or offspring, never to dullness, weakness, or the injury of your own or another’s peace or reputation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Humility&lt;/strong&gt; – Imitate Jesus and Socrates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Productivity, Self-Improvement, Life Lessons"></category><category term="benjamin-franklin"></category><category term="self-improvement"></category><category term="productivity"></category><category term="habits"></category><category term="personal-growth"></category><category term="humor"></category><category term="life-lessons"></category><category term="systems-thinking"></category><category term="history"></category><category term="learning"></category><category term="community"></category><category term="curiosity"></category></entry></feed>